Guide to the Philosophy and Social Science Manuscripts Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Philosophy and social science manuscripts collection
1866-1967
MS 644
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
(10 boxes)
An artificial collection of notes, lectures, student papers, scrapbooks, and writings relating to the study and teaching of the academic disciplines in the social sciences including economics, education, psychology, political science, philosophy, and sociology, 1866-1967. The papers of Charles Andrews Armstrong Bennett, Albert Bushnell Hart, Wilmon Henry Sheldon, Wilbur Marshall Urban, and Alfred North Whitehead are included.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by individuals whose papers are included in the collection.
Scope and Contents
The primary purpose of this register is to provide the researcher with a convenient guide to collections of manuscripts in the Sterling Memorial Library which, owing to their content or provenance, fall into the social science category, but which are too small to warrant separate descriptions.
For the present purpose "Social Science" has been broadly defined to include all those disciplines which were historically derived from Moral Philosophy in the mid-nineteenth century, together with certain related subject areas. Thus, the Philosophy and Social Science Manuscripts Group includes manuscripts relating to psychology, philosophy, education, law, economics, and political science. This group does not include manuscripts related to the humanities and the fine arts nor to those disciplines which derived from Natural Philosophy; those have been described separately in the guides to the Humanities and Fine Arts Manuscripts Group and the Natural Science Manuscripts Group respectively.
It should be re-emphasized that there are a number of separate large collections relating to philosophy and the social sciences that have been separately described and are not included in this register.
Consult the Chief Research Archivist, Manuscripts and Archives, for further information about all of these collections.
Biographical / Historical
CHARLES A. A. BENNETT (1885-1930)
Charles Andrew Armstrong Bennett was born in Ireland in 1885. He received his B.A. from Queen's College, Oxford, in 1908, and his Ph.D. from Yale in 1913. He taught philosophy at Yale until 1929. In 1923 he published A Philosophical Study of Mysticism and in 1931 a series of his lectures was published under the title The Dilemma of Religious Knowledge. Bennett died in 1930.
* * * * *
WILBUR M. URBAN (1873-1952)
Wilbur Marshall Urban was born in 1873, received an A.B. from Princeton in 1895 and a Ph.D. from Leipzig in 1897. He taught at various colleges, including Princeton and Dartmouth, and became professor of philosophy at Yale in 1931, where he was also chairman of the department. In 1941 he became professor emeritus. Urban died in 1952.
* * * * *
ALBERT BUSHNELL HART (1854-1943)
Albert Bushnell Hart was born in 1854, received his A.B. from Harvard in 1880 and his Ph.D. from Freidburg, Baden, in 1883. He taught history and government at Harvard from 1883, becoming professor in 1897 and professor emeritus in 1926. He has written and edited numerous volumes on American history and government. Hart died in 1943.
* * * * *
WILMON H. SHELDON (1875-)
Wilmon H. Sheldon was born in Newton, Massachusetts on April 4, 1875. He graduated from Harvard in 1895 from which he also received his M.A. in 1896 and his Ph.D. in philosophy in 1899. Sheldon taught philosophy at the University of Wisconsin, 1899-1900; Harvard, 1901-1903; Columbia, 1903-1905; Princeton, 1905-1909; and Dartmouth, 1909-1920, before coming to Yale, where he was professor of philosophy from 1920 and emeritus professor from 1943. Among his most important works are: Strife and Systems and Productive Duality (1918), America's Progressive Philosophy (1942), and Process and Polarity (1944).
* * * * *
ALFRED NORTH WHITEHEAD, 1861-1947
Alfred North Whitehead was born at Ramsgate, England on February 15, 1861. He received his B.A. from Trinity College, Cambridge in 1884 and an M.A. in 1887. Whitehead lectured on mathematics at Trinity College from, 1885 to 1911 and at the University of London from 1911 to 1924. In 1924 he joined the faculty of Harvard University as professor of philosophy, becoming emeritus professor in 1936.
Economics; Education; Law; Philosophy; Political science; Psychology; Social sciences; New Haven (Conn.); Sociology; Educators; Social scientists; Bennett, Charles A. (Charles Andrew Armstrong), 1885-1930; Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943; Kant, Immanuel, 1724-1804; Sheldon, Wilmon Henry, 1875-; Urban, Wilbur Marshall, 1873-1952; Whitehead, Alfred North, 1861-1947; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Graduate Philosophy Club
- CHARLES A. A. BENNETT
  Scope and Contents
  This group of papers consists almost entirely of notes on various philosophical topics, some of which were apparently taken while Bennett was a graduate student; others appear to be notes for his own lectures. There are also a few lectures on the philosophy of religion, two items of correspondence, copies of examinations, a few students' papers and some printed material relating to the first world war.
  It should be noted that originally this material was mixed with, and so mistakenly identified as, that of Wilbur Urban, Bennett's successor at Yale (q.v.). That material which is dated or signed is almost certainly Bennett's, but it is possible that some of Urban's papers remain with Bennett's.
  - Correspondence
    - [Gamed?] S.R., undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - [Sevain?] Joseph (enclosing notes), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Philosophy - General
    - Course of study (clipping) [Introductory lecture?], 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ethics
    - Assignments and bibliographies, 1915-1920, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Clippings and pamphlets, 1914-1919, 1923-1925, 1928 undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Examinations, 1910-1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Examinations and questions, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Notes: Introductory, subjects A - B, 1919-1924, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Notes: subjects C - D, 1924-1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Notes: subjects E - L, [1919?] 1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Notes: subjects M - P, 1919-1920, 1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Notes: subjects S - W, miscellaneous, 1925-1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Students' papers, 1916, 1922, 1925 1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - History of Philosophy
    - Miscellaneous notes and printed matter, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Examinations, 1910-1926 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Examinations and questions, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Notes: subjects A - E, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - History of Philosophy
    - Notes: subjects F - L, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Notes: subjects M - S, miscellaneous, 1921-1922, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Logic
    - Assignments, examinations and questions Newspaper clipping, 1912, 1924, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Mysticism
    - Bibliographies, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Notes: outlines for seminar, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - subjects B - H, [1914?] undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Notes: subjects J - V, miscellaneous student paper, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Philosophy of History
    - Bibliography, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Notes (including notes on lectures by W.E. Hocking), 1910-1911, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Papers and reports by C.A. Bennett, 1910-1911 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Philosophy of Nature [Philosophy of Science]
    - Assignments, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Bibliographies, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Examinations and questions, 1913-1914 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Philosophy of Religion
    - Assignments and outline of course, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Bibliographies, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Examinations and questions, 1910-1914, 1926, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Lectures and outline notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Lecture notes, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Subjects B - O, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Philosophy of Religion
    - Notes: on problems of religious knowledge, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Notes: miscellaneous, 1913, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Reports and students' papers, [1911.] undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Student paper, F.M. Meek., undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
      General
      See also: Wilbur M. Urban
  - Spinoza
    - Assignments, bibliographies, examination, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
      See also: box 1, folder 14
  - War
    - Newspaper clippings, 1914-1915, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1914-1915, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Notes on a speech by Norman Angell, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Pamphlets, 1913-1915, undated (Box 4, Folder 41-42)
    - Christianity and Contemporary Thought: Some Difficulties 3 essays submitted for the J.A. Porter Prize, 1909 (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - The Value of Mysticism, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 100)
    - Index to The Philosophical Study of Mysticism (Box 10, Folder 101)
- WILBUR M. URBAN
  These papers contain a large number of papers written for Urban by his students, mainly on ethics and on Kant. There are also two items of correspondence and a book manuscript, God and the Historians and Other Studies in the Philosophy of History, written by Urban in 1949.
  It should be noted that this material was originally mixed with the materials of Charles A. A. Bennett, Urban's predecessor at Yale (q.v.). Although the two groups of material have been separated as far as possible, some of Urban's material may still be in Bennett's papers.
  - Correspondence
    - from: Kujawa, Jan (enclosed writings) to: Otrander, Harry J., 1936 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Student Papers
    - Abercrambie, Dan, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Adelberg, A., 1936 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Beach, Waldo, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - "J.D.", undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Duce, Leonard A., undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Entberg, Barbara, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Eshleman, Martin, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Few, Lyne S., 1938 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Finch, H.L., 1938 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Gamley, John, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Harvey, Fred G., 1933 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Lane, Elizabeth B., 1938-1939, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Lotspeich, R., undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - McGarvey, John P., undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - MacPartland, John, undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Martin, Byrne, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Meek, F.M., Mitchell, W.M, undated (Box 5, Folder 51)
      See also: Charles A.A. Bennett
    - Pope, Liston, 1937-1938 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Prowell, Clean F., 1939 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Richardson, N.E., 1935 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Saltman, S., 1930 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Stephens, R.G., 1934 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Stuyard, Frederick, [1941?] (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Thompson, W. Mcllwaine, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Tseo, Ping-I, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Wiener, A., undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Williamson, James H., undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Wilson, Clyde D., undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Woyke, Drank H., undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Fragment, undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - List of Students, undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Writings
    - Book: God and the Historians and Other Studies in the Philosophy of History, Chaps I - V, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Book: God and the Historians... ,Chaps VI - IX, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 59)
- ALBERT BUSHNELL HART
  These papers consist of a series of scrapbooks concerning various aspects of elections and voting behavior with the exception of one scrapbook pertaining to political corruption and some notes about the aldermen of New Haven. The material from the scrapbooks includes clippings from newspapers, magazines and books; pamphlets; and notes, papers, and reports by students. Among the student papers there are a few letters from Hart to students about their papers. Also in the papers are letters from Edward Gaylord Bourne (q.v.) concerning his book, Spain in America, published in the American Nation series which Hart edited.
  - Board of Aldermen of New Haven, description of., undated (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Elections
    - Bribery - penalties and remedies, clippings, undated (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Campaign Funds: clippings, students' papers, 1896-1897, 1900-1906, undated (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Corrupt Practices Acts: clippings, pamphlets students' papers, 1892, 1894, 1904-1906, 1911-1917, undated (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - Corruption - illegal voting: clippings, pamphlet, students' papers, 1903-1904, 1906, 1910, undated (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Corruption of voters: clippings, pamphlet, students' papers, 1886,1889, 1892-1894, 1904-1914, undated (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Deals and Fusion: clippings, poster, student paper, 1910-1922, undated (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Expenses: clippings, 1906-1907, 1910 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Elections
    - Frauds - example in Chicago. Clippings, notes, student paper., 1898, 1914, undated (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Supreme Court of Illinois: Allerton, Swift, et al. vs. Hopkins - brief for appellants, reply for appelent., 1895 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Frauds - examples in Chicago (con'd) Supreme Court of Illinois: Allerton, Swift, et al. vs. Hopkins - abstract of record, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Intimidation: Clippings, pamphlets, students' papers, 1896, 1904-1908, 1916, undated (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - Intimidation (con'd): pamphlet, 1907 (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - Participation of voters: clippings, pamphlet, students' papers, 1887-1907, undated (Box 7, Folder 72)
    - Reforms: clippings and pamphlets, 1908-1918, undated (Box 7, Folder 73)
    - Suffrage: qualifications, tangible clippings, notes, students' papers, 1920, 1890-1891, 1896, 1906, undated (Box 7, Folder 74)
    - Voting - Compulsory: Letter to Hart from Adams, Charles F., 1892 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Clippings and notes, 1891, 1915, 1918 undated (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Voting: Counting of Votes. Clippings, Pamphlets, student paper, 1892, 1896, 1906-1907, 1910-1916, undated (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Voting: count of votes, recount: clippings, student paper, 1906-1907, 1910, 1917, undated (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Voting: Proportional: Clippings, Pamphlets, Student's Paper, 1908-1920, undated (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Political Corruption
    - Instances of: clippings and pamphlet, 1897, 1906-1915, undated (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Letters from Edward Gaylord Bourne, 1902-1905 (Box 8, Folder 79a)
    - Letters to Edward Gaylord Bourne, 1902-1907 (Box 8, Folder 79b)
    - Letters to Albert Bushnell Hart, 1905-1914 (Box 8, Folder 79c)
    - Albert B. Hart's editor's introduction to Spain in America by Edward G. Bourne; memoranda and reprints, 1904 (Box 8, Folder 79)
- WILMON H. SHELDON
  This group of papers consists primarily of manuscript drafts of his books, Rational Religion: The Philosophy of Christian Love, published in 1962, and Sex and Salvation, published in 1955. In addition, there are a few notes on religion and metaphysics and an article on Sheldon's philosophy by Peter H. Hare.
  - Articles
    - "W. H. Sheldon's Philosophy of Polarity: A Metaphilosophy" by Peter H. Hare, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 80)
    - (Reprints), 1905, 1923, 1929, 1947, 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - Letters
    - to W. Sheldon, [1943], 1957, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - from Cornelia Greer Le Boutillier, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Manuscripts
    - "The Evolution of Love" (Box 9, Folder 84)
    - Rational Religion: The Philosophy of Christian Love, early draft, Preface, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 85)
    - Rational Religion: The Philosophy of Christian Love, early draft, Chap. I, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - Rational Religion: The Philosophy of Christian Love, early draft, Chap. II, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - Rational Religion: The Philosophy of Christian Love, incomplete typed draft Chap. II (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - Rational Religion: The Philosophy of Christian Love, early draft, Chap. III (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - Rational Religion: The Philosophy of Christian Love, early draft, Chap. IV (Box 9, Folder 90)
    - Sex and Salvation, draft, Chap. I and II (Box 9, Folder 91)
    - Sex and Salvation, draft, Chap. III and IV (Box 9, Folder 92)
    - Sex and Salvation, draft, Chap. V and VI (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - Sex and Salvation, draft, Chap. VII and VIII (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Notes
    - on religion (Box 9, Folder 95)
    - on metaphysics (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Personal papers and memorabilia (Box 9, Folder 97)
- ALFRED NORTH WHITEHEAD
  This collection consists of a bound typescript of student notes taken from lectures of A.N. Whitehead at Harvard University from 1926 to 1937. The notes were compiled by: George P. Conger, William K. Frankena, A.H. Johnson John L. Mothershead, Jr., W. V. Quine, and Edward Schouten Robinson, and the entire collection compiled and typed by members of the Graduate Philosophy Club of Yale University in 1966. A copy of the table of contents follows.
  - Notes from "Lectures of A. N. W. at Harvard" Compiled by students, 1926-1937 (Box 10, Folder 98)
    See: Charles A. A. Bennett